There are 11 common mistakes that a lot
of people make when they take
supplements. Now, the first thing I want
to mention is that I hear this a lot. We
don't really need to take supplements
because we can get all we need from our
diet. And it's almost impossible to get
vitamin D from food. So, it's not
actually very easy to get all of our
nutrients even if we ate a really good
diet. Not to mention certain foods that
deplete us of nutrients, especially if
you're doing a lot of refined carbs.
Okay, number one, let's talk about
timing. Okay, during the day. When
should you take your supplements?
Personally, I like to take almost all of
my supplements in the morning because I
want all these co-actors to be available
in the first part of the day when I need
more energy. In fact, I switch my
intermittent fasting pattern where I'm
doing two meals. One is breakfast and
then a late lunch and then I don't have
a dinner. That seems to work. And the
reason I did that is because it gives me
more energy during the day rather than
doing fasting. and then eating late at
night when I don't need the energy
before I go to bed. Now, as far as
taking electrolytes right before bed, I
don't really recommend it because
electrolytes can push fluid out of your
body. Now, as far as vitamin D goes,
some people do better to take the
vitamin D in the morning. Some people do
better right before bed. It tends to
help them sleep better. You can
experiment with that. The other thing I
want to mention about the timing is that
you don't want to take any calcium
supplements right before you eat because
calcium neutralizes the stomach acid and
it's going to inhibit your digestion.
The next mistake I want to talk about is
taking too many supplements at one time
and trying to swallow them. I personally
use myself as a human guinea pig for a
long time. I've tried pretty much every
single nutrient vitamin cleanse
alternative program you can imagine. And
um one time long ago I decided to do a
gallbladder flush. In this gallbladder
flush you take beetroot supplements and
olive oil. I took a hand of these
beetroot supplements, put them in my
mouth and wash them down with 12 ounces
of oil. Big big mistake. I should have
used some water and I should have taken
a little bit at a time because those
beet supplements got stuck in my
esophagus. And it was like I started
getting chest pain. I thought I was
going to die like a heart attack. Oh my
gosh, I'm going to die from taking
supplements. So, I just kind of laid in
a bowl and just pushed through it and
somehow I survived. But I don't
recommend that. Those are very, very
scary. Some people do better just taking
their supplements with a meal. it seems
to go down easier. Next mistake is this.
If you're trying to solve a health
problem, whatever it is, and you
introduce a lot of different supplements
at one time, you're not going to know
what worked. So, always introduce them
one at a time, especially if you're
trying to solve some health problem. The
next mistake is thinking these vitamins
are going to work if your diet sucks. I
have a personal example of this. Yes, I
was eating too many carbs at one time,
but I wasn't consuming enough protein,
especially for breakfast. And no matter
how many vitamins I took, I was still
tired. What I really needed was protein.
Once I had protein, I'm like, "Oh my
gosh, everything works now." But also,
if you're eating too many carbs and
things like that, you're going to get a
lot of bloating and um I don't care how
many vitamins you take for this or that,
it's not going to create the effect.
Next mistake is going for the cheapest
vitamin possible, especially these one a
days. If you read the label, which I
have right here, I'm going to show you
the first ingredient, calcium carbonate,
which is the type of calcium and cement.
So, they're putting the cheapest
vitamins you could possibly imagine,
mostly made from petroleum and
chemicals. A lot of the vitamin
companies out there um are owned by
either chemical companies, big pharma,
or some of the junk food brands. What
I'm observing is they're not going for
quality ingredients. They get the
cheapest possible, especially when you
get into antioxidants like beta
carotene, for example, and you're taking
it synthetically. There's some side
effects. It shows that it increases your
risk for cancer. Of course, they're not
doing a comparison with that study on
using antioxidants from actual food. No,
it's the synthetic version. It's
probably not the best way to do it. And
the other thing you'll notice with the
synthetics is the RDAs are the same.
Supplying 100% 100% 100%. In nature, you
don't have that. And of course, you have
fillers, you have uh colorings, and
sometimes people think that there's no
difference between vitamins. The
synthetics are the same as natural.
Well, I don't think so. Now, there are a
couple vitamins that I think are fine to
take synthetically. One is niacin and
then the other one is benotamine but for
some of the other vitamins I would try
to go more natural or get the vitamins
in the natural complex that nature has
provided. Now let's talk about the
mistake sometimes people make with
supplements and drug interactions.
They're on a medication that's creating
an effect. Okay? And then they want to
take a supplement that also creates the
same effect. Doctors don't like that
because then that might make the problem
worse. So if you're taking a medication
for high blood pressure and then you
take a supplement to also help lower
your high blood pressure and you end up
with low blood pressure, then that might
be an issue. So you need to check with
your doctor so they can monitor that
because I mean my thought is why not
introduce something natural. I'll give
you an example. Let's say you're
diabetic and you're taking metformin.
Well, bourberine also creates an effect
very similar to metformin. Why not work
with the doctor to just take less of the
metformin because that could have some
side effects? One thing I want to say
about antibiotics is that you should
always take a probiotic when you're
taking an antibiotic so you can at least
salvage the good bacteria. But here's
the thing. If you're on medication,
let's say for example, for high blood
pressure and you're taking magnesium and
all of a sudden your blood pressure
starts going too low, is that really a
bad thing? Why not just get with the
doctor to take less of that medication?
Because magnesium is such an important
uh natural remedy for everything related
to the heart. One of the worst
medications you can take for your liver,
which is over-the-counter, is Tylenol.
You might want to try milk thistle. An
herbal supplement that can actually
minimize the damage of your liver from
some of these other medications. Next
mistake a lot of people make with
supplements is that there's certain
vitamin or mineral interactions that
people need to know about. For example,
if you're taking high doses of vitamin
D3
without magnesium,
this could be a problem. You need
magnesium for vitamin D to do its job.
And without magnesium, vitamin D can't
work. And also, taking high levels of
zinc over a long period of time, you can
end up with a copper deficiency. So,
just realize that a lot of times these
minerals go in uh pairs like sodium and
potassium. If you're consuming a lot of
salt without potassium, that could be a
problem. This is why I don't recommend
taking one mineral for a long period of
time, especially if you're doing high
dosage. I would rather you take the one
mineral in a blend of other minerals or
trace minerals just to make sure that
you don't create another problem. All
right. Next point I want to bring up is
taking advice from someone that gives
you an opinion about vitamins that's not
really based on a a good evaluation.
There's not enough time in school to
really fully understand biochemistry.
All you have time to do is memorize
things like this Krebs cycle, pass the
test, and move on to the next subject.
So, there's a big difference between
learning and understanding and
memorizing. They're not the same thing.
So, you really want to get opinions from
people that have a lot of experience in
the area of what you're trying to get an
opinion on. Like, you wouldn't want to
take marriage advice from someone that's
never been married. And one last point
about this, I think it's really
important. A lot of the institutions and
journals do not like to publish anything
positive on vitamin D. Now, why would
that be? Because it competes with the
drug companies and vitamin D is very
inexpensive because you can get it from
the sun. All right. Next uh mistake I'm
going to mention with supplements is not
taking high enough doses. There's two
reasons why people take supplements. One
is to compensate from not having enough
from their diet. The other reason is to
create a therapeutic effect. And there's
a lot of other reasons why high doses of
certain vitamins are good. There's
actually quite a few genetic weaknesses
that make it more difficult to absorb um
certain nutrients. I recently had over
20 people get their DNA testing on
vitamin D and a 100% of them had at
least one genetic problem or weakness
with either absorbing vitamin D or
converting. So the solution is just to
take a little bit more. Another common
vitamin that I think people are not
taking enough of is vitamin B1. I mean
the RDAs for vitamin B1 is ridiculous.
Ridiculous. it's not going to do
anything. Like they're 100 years old and
they're just based on what you would
need to prevent a deficiency. They're
not based on correcting something or to
create a therapeutic benefit. The other
thing is if your stomach is not acid
enough, it's too alkaline, you're not
going to be able to absorb the minerals,
you're not going to be able to break
down B12 because you have to break down
that protein that's connected to it. in
which case you would need to take, you
know, betane hydrochloride to acidify
the stomach so you can absorb some of
these nutrients. All right, the next
point I want to talk about is if you are
a vegan, right, you're not getting
animal sources. So, you really want to
make sure you take additional nutrients
on top of your diet because you're going
to be deficient. You would need to take
B12. You need D3, omega-3 fatty acids.
If you don't want to get it from fish
sources, you can get it from algae,
iron, zinc, iodine, and calcium. Now,
let's get to the last one. Dosing. And
when I'm talking about dosing, I'm
talking about how many times of week do
you need vitamin D. This is so so
important simply because vitamin D is
the most important vitamin because of
what happens when you're deficient. the
RDAs that they originally came up with
which is you know 600 IUs is sufficient
but there's another system that a lot of
people do not know about and this system
is called the paracrine autorine system
so this system is mainly dependent on
either the sun converting the
cholesterol in your skin to vitamin D or
the vitamin D in your food or the
vitamin D in your supplements ments and
the halflife for that is like 24 hours.
So after 24 hours it's it's pretty much
gone. So if you're trying to support
your immune system, you need to be
taking vitamin D every single day or
getting sun every single day or it's
very likely you're going to be
deficient. The amount that I would
recommend as a maintenance would be no
less than 10,000 I use. That's not
unreasonable. It might sound like a lot.
It's not. But the dangers of having a
vitamin D deficiency are much much
greater than having any excess. And
since we're ending off on this vitamin D
topic, if you have not seen this
interview with Professor Hollis, who is
the pioneer in vitamin D research, you
have to check it out. We go into this
topic a lot more in depth, and I put
that video up right here. Check it out.